[SPEAKER_04]: So, this is a question that's come up recently from quite a few people.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I've just sort of paraphrased it into one.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, a friend asks, the more I realize that it's impossible for any of my activities to be separate from this body, the nature of the body, the more I sense the confinement that Bhante often mentions, and the more oppressive it feels.
[SPEAKER_04]: As a result, I begin to feel like everything I do is worthless, pointless, self-loathing, sadness, and this overwhelms me.
[SPEAKER_04]: I believe that such thoughts are rooted in ill-will and a wish to just give up, just to give up the practice, become lazy.
[SPEAKER_04]: I would appreciate it if you could give me a few tips on how to go through this kind of state.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, by going through it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the self-loathing, the worldlessness, the confinement, that is, yeah, all factual.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the reason why it is painful, it's because your views, your habits, your expectations, are still kind of referred to from the point of view of centrality.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the central pleasures, the ambition, the inspiration, spilling out in the world, that is still where your criterias are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Habitually.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure, now you started reflecting, you saw, no, that doesn't add up, it's actual confinement, it's sense restraint, all of that, and now this is felt unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's felt unpleasantly, not because in and of itself, but it's felt unpleasantly because you're still not fully abandoned the previous kind of views and criterias and notions.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the self-loathing
[SPEAKER_02]: aspect of of that confinement is due to basically your kind of addiction of sensuality still being there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the only way to then, for that addiction to to sort of dissipate, is to endure the self-loathing and don't go back to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: They will then re-value it, re-infuse it again with the old value, which will then remove the self-loathing
[SPEAKER_02]: From being immediately felt, and put it back into your framework.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, sooner or later, when you don't have enough sensuality, you're going to go back, and you're going to start self-loathing again.
[SPEAKER_02]: When the distractions sort of disappear, self-loathing is back.
[SPEAKER_02]: Confinement is back.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't deal with it by doing this or that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You deal with it by not going back to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, the self-loathing disappears, confinement remains, as a factual thing, that it's not unpleasant anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when the confinement remains, no ātavāda can exist outside of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you go through the withdrawals and endure the self-loathing, without breaking the precepts, without falling back onto the sensuality, without disregarding the training, you will be destroying the first three fetters.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, the risk, you might go mad, if you lose your restraint.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you, eh... if you get overwhelmed and act out, you won't get mad if your mind is just spinning out of control.
[SPEAKER_02]: You get mad by acting madly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you lose sense restraint and if you don't guard your sense doors, that's how you will then lose control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not otherwise.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, if you don't do anything on account of it, it will have to come down.
[SPEAKER_02]: How long that takes?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, depends on how addicted you were before.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I reckon, it would take a while, because we were all quite addicted before.
[SPEAKER_02]: If we weren't, we would have been born in the Buddha's time and become Arahant by now.
[SPEAKER_04]: You start, yeah, virtue, sense of strength.
[SPEAKER_04]: Eventually, you start feeling the confinement that you are in.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're feeling confined by the aggregates, crushed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which becomes very uninspiring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where's the bliss?
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing's worth doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just pressure, pressure, pressure.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're just enclosed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Here I am, enclosed.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do I do now?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, there's pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's just pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you just keep following that same principle of... that you've been... that God... You want to get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not trying to get rid of that pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: Enduring it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, again, you can be enduring it for the sake of getting it... getting rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll endure this when it will go away.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll endure it so it goes away.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have to understand...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do I do then?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'm confined now, on account of sense-restraint, nothings we're doing, self-loading, what do I do next?
[SPEAKER_04]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, discerning the nature of that, again, is... Yeah, okay, yeah, something else, what is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do I do then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there anything for me to do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you need to do something?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Confinement is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's painful because you want to do something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, include that question in the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I did.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the pain is still here.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, keep including it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep including the wish to step out and do something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Other than guarding the context, as we said many times.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then what?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I include the wish to step outside of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now I can just relax and do stuff?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, just... Because I included the wish?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, just keep going.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or do I still not do certain things and do certain things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, sure, there are, like, things to be endured, things to be developed, other things to be developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, no, in this particular example, I'm confined, you're all giving me advice of what to do,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you just don't do... What is it that I don't do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't break any precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't act out of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as... What do I do next?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do I do next?
[SPEAKER_02]: Confinement will be confining even more, because you're trying to outrun it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you do factually need to stop doing certain things, stop resisting that, so you can calm down, but not too far.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the right balance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Too tight and too loose.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if it's too much, I just can't bear it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't even think about the dhamma anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just so unpleasant, so painful, so self-loathing.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just should not go back to sensuality and distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything else fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll sit, I'll walk, I'll sleep.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have something to say, I don't have to practice, I won't practice because it's too painful, but I won't go to sensuality, I won't lose the sense restraint, and I won't act out of desire, greed and distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just don't do... literally, don't do anything, which includes don't go back to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Isn't it like you're still doing that discernment of this is unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you won't be doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can be doing it, but the time will come where even that cannot be sustained.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just have to give it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just too painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what I'm saying is that will have to come, and when you give it up, give it up, but not all the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you have not been doing certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have been not, you know, breaking the precepts, you have not been chasing sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, now when you give up the practice as well,
[SPEAKER_02]: Chasing sensuality and breaking the precepts would be doing, would be requiring effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now, that would also fall under the principle, no, but I won't do anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: I won't practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: I won't do anything that exerts the effort, because just the thought of effort, it is just too painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, okay, fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have to make any effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: When that point comes, just drop all the effort, including effort towards sensuality and breaking the precepts that you have been keeping beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because, as you just said, like, you know, chasing sensuality requires effort and maintenance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's a doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, if somebody, before they have been sufficiently withdrawn, decides to drop the effort because it's too painful, well, sensuality is effortless for them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they haven't been withdrawn from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, when they drop the effort, they'll do the effortless stuff, which is pursue the sense desires.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why the behavior, as we would say, needs to be developed beforehand, the purity of the body behavior.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when that has been sufficiently endured, and you reach the wall in terms of, I can't even think about a dhamma anymore, it's just unbearable, fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, just remember things that you have not been doing, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't have to do anything new.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just stay from... abstaining from certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's effortless.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, whatever's there, you are discerning it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just not on account of your own intense terms, out of trying to get rid of the pain and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: You would see that even, kind of, giving up, in a sense, that effort, or even the, like, you know, it's so painful, and I need to, kind of, keep bearing in mind this pain, or I keep, like, what if I let it go?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it might be pleasant, it might be peaceful, it might be okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's nearly, in itself, kind of, something to relinquish, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea to, kind of, that it, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to keep bearing the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it might change.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might be painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's...
[SPEAKER_01]: It is never in your control anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's never in your control anyway.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you see, you were trying to control it, in a sense, even... Yeah, well, that's just how the pains of striving work.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to determine which means going to result, you're going to kind of overdo the tightening, because it was too loose.
[SPEAKER_02]: When things are too loose, you don't just magically stop right in the right tune.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you're going to be over-tightening it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, oh, it's going to snap now, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: So let me loosen it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now you realize, okay, let me loosen it, but not as loose as it was before.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you will find the right tune, the right balance.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, see, when you are already tight to the point of snapping,
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, what do I do now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever I tell you to do, if it's done on that, on that, on account of that intention, will be another twist for tightening it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do you do now is just nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Also, does that mean I go and break the precepts?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's not nothing, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, do nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm sleepy, I'm hungry, I'll walk, I'll be silent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'll go and distract him.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, that's too loose.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, I'll sit the whole night and think about dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's too tight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do I do now?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I do now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I need to know what do I do now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that that unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_02]: And you realize then it was only unpleasant because you kept trying to sort of get out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then it's, well, actually, I don't know what to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not that unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know what I will not do.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's all I need to know.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to know specific steps that I need to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just need to not forget what I must not do.
[SPEAKER_02]: And not doing things is effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you become an island to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you realize, oh, the line.
[SPEAKER_02]: The line is the action, intentionally acting out of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not this thought, that thought, this moment, my moment, sensation, slept, forgot, I'm so overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only if I intentionally choose to open the door, let the flood in, that's how it gets in.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I don't do it, doesn't matter what's outside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cannot flood me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Intention rooted in greed, aversion, distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Abstain from those and don't do anything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you'll be fine.